<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Distraction | Adventures in brine]]></title>
  <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/categories/distraction/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-23T23:21:18+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rich.k3r.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Richard Kimber]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shutting the World Out]]></title>
    <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/01/22/shutting-the-world-out/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-22T20:18:34+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/01/22/shutting-the-world-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is never enough time. Last year in particular, it always felt like there wasn&rsquo;t enough time in the day.  Running a company, where your work is also the primary source of income, is no easy task. I was always looking for ways of squeezing more hours out of day; tweaking processes, finding better tools, writing scripts. It&rsquo;s become a bit of an obsession for me, finding &ldquo;better&rdquo; ways to get more stuff done. I was pretty good at it, I think I still am. But as the end of last year drew in, it became clear that I was spreading myself too thin.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I was a manager, a sales person, a support desk, a developer, and was switching these hats constantly throughout the day. My goal on any given day, was to get to the end of the day without any major mishaps. If I managed to progress at all, in terms of significant progression of a project or a more efficient way of doing something, well that was amazing.</p>

<p>The problem was concentration, I couldn&rsquo;t stay focused on a single task, without being distracted by someone or something craving my attention. We experimented with a few different ways of tackling this:</p>

<ol>
<li>Switching off access to email at specific parts of the day.</li>
<li>We decided that I should not answer the phone.</li>
<li>Further than this, I wouldn&rsquo;t participate in a phone call unless it was me that initiated it. If someone wanted to talk to me, a time would be arranged for me to ring them back.</li>
<li>Allocated time to perform specific tasks.</li>
</ol>


<p>These feel obvious to me now, but they weren&rsquo;t back then and had a huge impact on my ability to get through work. Even combined though, these were not the silver bullets I was after. I&rsquo;m too nosey for one thing, if someone else picked up the phone, my ears would prick up, brain on overdrive wondering what they wanted and were the requirements being dealt with correctly. And who can blame me, it&rsquo;s my company after all.</p>

<p>I needed a way of maintaining concentration, without completely removing myself from the office. My salvation came in another, now startlingly obvious, epiphany; headphones. It&rsquo;d never really occurred to me in the past to try headphones, because in the past I&rsquo;ve typically opted for in-ear earphones, which are uncomfortable over long periods of time. I&rsquo;m also pretty negative on headphones in an office environment as rule, because I hate sound leakage. But I didn&rsquo;t see that I had an option and it&rsquo;s made the world of difference. <a href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/01/20/finding-a-pair-of-headphones/">My earphones</a> use noise reduction to completely immerse me in the task at hand.</p>

<p>An unexpected and corny side effect of the headphones has been trust. I am nosey because I believe I need to be involved in every decision, that my opinion always needs to be considered. Switching on the headphones has demonstrated to me that  I&rsquo;m not (always) the centre of the universe, and that many facets of the company can run without my constant interference.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m okay with that, because I spend a lot more time on the stuff I like doing now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finding a Pair of Headphones]]></title>
    <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/01/20/finding-a-pair-of-headphones/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-20T22:38:34+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/01/20/finding-a-pair-of-headphones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When looking for a pair of headphones, it was important to me that they shut out as much outside noise as possible and be comfortable for long periods of time. I&rsquo;ve never spent more than £15 on a pair of earphones (typically in ear), so when you type in those requirements into a search engine, you should expect quite a shock!</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I&rsquo;d read on a couple of developer blogs, that &ldquo;around ear&rdquo; design was the way to go for comfort. Also, that <a href="http://www.audio-technica.com/cms/headphones/99aff89488ddd6b1/">Audio Technica ATH-M50X</a>s were a good choice for the money, at around £100. I&rsquo;m a long time fan of Sennheiser, and came across the <a href="http://en-uk.sennheiser.com/over-ear-headphone-momentum-stereo">Momentum</a> range under my own steam. The &ldquo;around ear&rdquo; Momentum&rsquo;s are around £200 and are far and away the most gorgeous looking headphones I&rsquo;ve ever seen.</p>

<p>Feeling out of my depth though, I asked around a couple of friends. The response was unanimous. If you want to block out sound, it has to be the Bose Quiet Comfort range. The <a href="https://www.bose.co.uk/GB/en/home-and-personal-audio/headphones-and-headsets/acoustic-noise-cancelling-headphones/quietcomfort-25-headphones/">QC25</a> model is the latest and cost £270! Holy floor Batman, that was not going to be an off-the-cuff decision!</p>

<p>What makes a pair of headphones cost almost £300? The QC25 has acoustic noise cancellation, which I think is basically a series of microphones that detect outside noise, which the headphone then counteracts with a reverse wave, cancelling out the sound. It sounds cool, but I was also concerned the cancelation might work against me, I&rsquo;m quiet sensitive to electrical noise.</p>

<p>Working on the assumption that Bose aren&rsquo;t the only company capable of such feats, I also found the <a href="http://en-uk.sennheiser.com/wireless-bluetooth-headset-stereo-mm-550-x-travel">Sennheiser MM 550-X</a>, which purport to do the same as the QC25s, but with bluetooth and surround sound for the same price! At this point the prices were more like monopoly money in my head.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d seen these headphones online, but no way was I going to spend dollar until I&rsquo;d tried them on! I set out to two city centres and a shopping centre, where I found two Bose shops and a third shop that only had Bose headphones for you to try. Not a snifter of the other headphones!</p>

<p>The QC25s were incredible! The sound was beautiful and crisp. In the busy shopping centre, I switched the noise reduction on and the world slipped away. Wow. The &ldquo;anti sound&rdquo; wasn&rsquo;t noticeable to me in the shopping centre.</p>

<p>I wanted to make sure I was making the right choice though, so I hit the internet reviews. I needed noise reduction now, I wasn&rsquo;t going to spend a £100 on a pair of earphones that didn&rsquo;t disconnect me from the world. So the question was, how good are the MM 550-Xs? Even the most glowing review of these headphones, that cited them as the best bluetooth headphones on the market, suggested that surround sound was best turned off and the noise reduction was not on par with the QC25. I was really attracted to the bluetooth, but noise reduction was becoming very important to me.</p>

<p>Fast forward a lot &ldquo;first world&rdquo; agonising and several attempts to find a shop that would allow me to try a decent selection of headphones. I conceded though and bought the QC25s.</p>

<p>In the silence of my home, I was initially stuck by two disappointments:</p>

<ol>
<li>The &ldquo;anti noise&rdquo; is audible if you&rsquo;re in a quiet environment. To me at least.</li>
<li>The headphones leak more noise to the outside than I&rsquo;d like at moderate volumes.</li>
</ol>


<p>Then I told myself to get a grip. Why would you use the noise reduction in a quiet environment any way. The headphones do leak more noise than I&rsquo;d like, but I am exceptionally picky in this area.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been using them for about two weeks now and I&rsquo;m entirely satisfied. At work I am blissful ignorance to the world around me. At home, Gravity Rush on the PS Vita is a completely new experience with these bad boys on.</p>

<p>I cannot overstate how comfy they are to wear and the case is invaluable as I am always lugging stuff around in my man bag.</p>

<p>I still have reservations over spending that amount of money on a pair of headphones, but the headphones themselves, I&rsquo;m doubtless are worth every penny.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
