<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Comics | Adventures in brine]]></title>
  <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/categories/comics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-29T22:20:27+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://rich.k3r.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Richard Kimber]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Comics: The DRM Effect]]></title>
    <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/03/05/comics-the-drm-effect/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-05T07:42:41+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/03/05/comics-the-drm-effect</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I transitioned from paper to digital, I didn&rsquo;t just reclaim floor space in my loft, I picked up a more eclectic taste in reading material as well. For the most part, I suspect happenstance of maturity in tastes and storage reclamation. One factor, that at least in part, can be attributed to my personal comic book renaissance, is DRM. Which is funny, because I bloody hate DRM.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>DRM exposes the shame that we don&rsquo;t really own anything. Buy &ldquo;A New Hope&rdquo; of VHS, then wait for the format to become obsolete. Buy it DRM through iTunes, has it really got any less of a shelf life. How many times have we bought the original Star Wars trilogy (to own), throughout our lives. I&rsquo;ve bought it three times, twice on VHS, once on DVD. I will not replace the DVDs, unless the movie industry goes DRM free or Disney release an irresistible boxset. Ah, shit.</p>

<p>At first, I took the approach with comics, that I still take with my digital movie collection, that DRM is a fact of life. If you want to see the movie, it&rsquo;s either DRM or a hard copy. I don&rsquo;t want a hard copy. As a side issue, this is why I have not seen Twelve Monkeys in such a long time (not available in the UK to stream, is never on the TV).</p>

<p>With comics, there is a third option that has just become a lot more popular. DRM-free comics. Look, I&rsquo;m not saying they&rsquo;re new, just that your options have recently increased, albeit at the sacrifice of other ethical issues. What am I talking about? Comixology, a firm favourite of mine for reading digital comics, made the monumental step of allowing creators to offer their comics DRM-free. This is a truly amazing step forward in my view. So, what about the ethics? Man it&rsquo;s annoying that they&rsquo;ve been taken over by (the UK tax dodging poster boys) Amazon.</p>

<p>I hate that I&rsquo;m so invested in this company.</p>

<ul>
<li>I use Amazon Prime, because they have some great streaming options. DRM protected.</li>
<li>I use Audible. Amazon &amp; DRM protected! But the best source of audio books I&rsquo;ve found.</li>
<li>I have a Kindle, because it&rsquo;s easily the best device for reading, which also ties in with Audible. Also DRM protected.</li>
<li>And now, now my comics are purchased through Amazon as well. Arrrgh. The one saving grace being that DRM is optional.</li>
</ul>


<p>Let&rsquo;s save my ethical crises for another post. It&rsquo;s unlikely that Marvel or DC are going to be clicking the &ldquo;DRM-free&rdquo; button anytime soon. Dark Horse have their own service which is still disappointingly DRM protected. All of which means that if you want a DRM-free comic book library, you have to look at other publishers.</p>

<p>2000 AD have been selling their entire digital catalogue,  DRM-free for a good while now, and they deserve nothing but praise for it. Because of this, I&rsquo;ve rekindled my love of their periodical, as well as discovering some real classic gems. Halo Jones is the one that comes immediately to mind. If I have one gripe with 2000 AD, it&rsquo;s its clunky checkout process. No ability to save card details or use Paypal. If the process of buying comics was easier, I&rsquo;d regrettably be spending more. I know this is true because of in spite of my ethical crises, the Comixology checkout process is smooth like butter. So smooth, it&rsquo;s a little unsettling at times.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t just read DRM-free comics. I read a few titles, like Powers, Hellboy &amp; Atomic Robo that are so far not free of their DRM shackles. Here though, I end this post with some DRM-free recommendations.</p>

<h2>2000 AD</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://shop.2000adonline.com/products/ballad_of_halo_jones">The Ballad of Halo Jones</a> - I love this book so much. It&#8217;a true space opera in comic form. Reminiscent of Ender&rsquo;s Game and Forever War.</li>
<li><a href="http://shop.2000adonline.com/digital/comics">2000 AD</a> - I&rsquo;m on #1679. So many stories, so much beautiful artwork. I couldn&rsquo;t hope to remember them all. Shakara!</li>
</ul>


<h2>Comixology</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.comixology.co.uk/Bitch-Planet/comics-series/30465">Bitch Planet</a> - I&rsquo;m three issues in, and it&rsquo;s really good. The art is so cool, very pulpy. The story has kicked off to a great start.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.comixology.co.uk/Elephantmen/comics-series/654">Elephantmen</a> - I admit, I&rsquo;ve not read this one in a little while, but I was happy to see it go DRM-free. I&rsquo;m hovering around #28. It&rsquo;s a gritty piece of work and I like how the different threads work together.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.comixology.co.uk/Morning-Glories/comics-series/4617">Morning Glories</a> - Not my usual bag, but the story is compelling. I&rsquo;m on #15.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.comixology.co.uk/Jack-Staff/comics-series/686">Jack Staff</a> - The artwork is awesome. The stories for the most part are great, with a lot of funny references, familiar to those of a British upbringing.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.comixology.co.uk/The-Life-After/comics-series/21882">The Life After</a> - I really love the art in this book. I&rsquo;m on #3, and so far, it&rsquo;s very original, very surreal.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Problem With Web Comics]]></title>
    <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/02/05/the-problem-with-web-comics/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-05T21:26:56+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/02/05/the-problem-with-web-comics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>That&rsquo;s right, I&rsquo;m going to have quick whinge about web comics. You know, comics of (more often than not) an incredibly high quality, provided for free by their talented creators. It seems like an entirely justifiable premise doesn&rsquo;t it? Well, maybe&hellip; Let&rsquo;s give it a go and see where we end up.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>You pick up a book, you read a chapter or two, stick a bookmark in, then set it down on you bedside table. The next time you pick that book up, you go straight to the bookmark and continue reading. I haven&rsquo;t done that for a while mind. I&rsquo;m a hoarder by nature, without the space to truly exercise the talent. So I made the decision a few years ago to go digital with all of my printed media, books, magazines and comics. It makes my inability to throw anything away, less of an issue.</p>

<p>The kindle makes reading a book very easy as a digital medium. I was more sceptical about whether I&rsquo;d get on with comics on a bright iPad screen, but the transition took and I&rsquo;m almost exclusively digital now. Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, paper is best - there is nothing like the smell of an old book - but digital is a good compromise. The only real issue I have with digital (as format) is that I am always scrabbling for something to read in the bath.</p>

<p>Okay, I&rsquo;m slowly getting off the point. The point I am trying to make is that, it took my a little while to buy into comics in a digital format, but once I was there, my appetite became insatiable. &ldquo;Need more input.&rdquo;</p>

<p>My taste in comics has changed quite a lot over the years. At the peak of my print comic reading, it was almost exclusively DC/Marvel cape books. Now, I read almost (there&rsquo;s that word again) no superhero books; my tastes are more fringe. I&rsquo;m looking for stories that surprise me in some way.</p>

<p>Enter web comics. Thank goodness, I thought we&rsquo;d never get there.</p>

<p>Not a totally altruistic endeavour on the part of the creator; web comics are a great way to demonstrate a new talent or get different ideas out there. Regardless of motive, &lsquo;free to read&rsquo; material is a win for the reader. It has led me personally to discover creators that I may not have found otherwise, and to purchases of those creator&rsquo;s commercial offerings. A memorable example of this happening, was after finding <a href="http://www.friendswithboys.com/">Friends With Boys</a> by <a href="http://www.faitherinhicks.com/">Faith Erin Hicks</a>, which led me to discovering books like The War at Ellsmere and Adventures of Superhero Girl.</p>

<p>With Friends With Boys, I started reading roughly halfway through the run. Having so much content already available got me hooked. I obsessively finished the rest of the story, ensuring to log on to the site for new content, the moment it was published. In this instance web comics really worked for me.</p>

<p>In other instances, web comics have also worked for me in the short strip format, like with <a href="http://oglaf.com/">Oglaf</a> (NSFW). Oglaf works, because a) the name is very easy to remember and b) the stories are very short and funny (and rude).</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m discussing virtues, when I should be discussing problems.</p>

<h2>Discoverability</h2>

<p>Really the only reliable way I&rsquo;ve had to find new web comics is by recommendation through <a href="http://io9.com/">io9</a>. I&rsquo;ve attempted to find other sources, but all too often the sites are outdated in style and content.</p>

<h2>Bookmarks</h2>

<p>If I&rsquo;m reading a purchased comic, I&rsquo;ll use <a href="https://www.comixology.co.uk/">Comixology</a> or <a href="http://www.bitolithic.com/comic-zeal/">Comic Zeal</a>. These apps are my &ldquo;easy reach&rdquo;, they&rsquo;re my bookmark.</p>

<p>Some web comics are published in blogs, some in more purpose built sites. Some web comics are published as little more than Javascript slideshows with no thought to browser history. Some sites read backwards (chronologically), some forwards.</p>

<p>Man, it&rsquo;s a mess if you just want to pick something up every now and then. It&rsquo;s enough to switch me off to most of them.</p>

<h2>Possible Solution</h2>

<p>The problem with web comics, I&rsquo;ve discovered while writing this post, is me (the reader). I expect too much I think, from something that is a) free and b) created by someone(s) who don&rsquo;t want spend their lives worrying over usability. I suspect they mainly want to write comics.</p>

<p>The solution, I&rsquo;ve often wondered, might be to have an episodic web comic publishing framework. A service that allowed content creators to upload at whatever frequency they liked, which would then be collected into an entity that could be navigated and bookmarked by the reader, through an app or a website.</p>

<p>The thing that has stopped me from creating such a service in the past (time aside), is the creator&rsquo;s original motive in uploading the comic in the first place.</p>

<ul>
<li>Would a delivery system such as the one I&rsquo;ve described, go against principles of the creator?</li>
<li>Does it remove the human element that encompasses a web comic?</li>
<li>Once the content is packaged in such a way, has it jumped ahead of its intended published form?</li>
<li>Are all those bloody adverts actually critical to the creator&rsquo;s original decision to publish in the first place?</li>
</ul>


<p>I don&rsquo;t know, maybe I&rsquo;ll have stab at that system in the future. If you&rsquo;ve made it to bottom of this post, I&rsquo;d be interested to hear how you manage your web comic reading. If you&rsquo;re a creator, I&rsquo;d be really interested in hearing about the thought process that goes into publishing a web comic, and whether you see a need for a better delivery system.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
