<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rebuttal | Adventures in brine]]></title>
  <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/categories/rebuttal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-19T07:57:25+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rich.k3r.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Richard Kimber]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Knowing Your Craft to the Rescue!]]></title>
    <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/02/12/knowing-your-craft-to-the-rescue/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-12T07:21:23+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/02/12/knowing-your-craft-to-the-rescue</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just finished reading <a href="http://alistapart.com/column/what-will-save-us-from-the-dark-side-of-pre-processors">What Will Save Us from the Dark Side of CSS Pre-Processors?</a> on <a href="http://alistapart.com/">A List Apart</a>. I found the title and initial tone of the post confounding. And well, I probably read the post in the first instance, to shout down the wildly unfair negative connotations attached to preprocessors.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The thing is, I love preprocessors. I love them so much that I&rsquo;m currently brewing a series of posts extolling the virtues of preprocessors. Then I&rsquo;m faced by a post by A List Apart (a site I have a lot of respect for), apparently prophesying the demise of these little wonders. I couldn&rsquo;t let the post go, what if they were right?</p>

<p>After all, its up to all of us to constantly question everything we believe to be true. Right? Right.</p>

<p>The arguments set forth for the problems with preprocessors are:</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://alistapart.com/column/what-will-save-us-from-the-dark-side-of-pre-processors#section2">Unmindful use of preprocessors creates bloated output.</a></li>
<li><a href="http://alistapart.com/column/what-will-save-us-from-the-dark-side-of-pre-processors#section3">By adding a layer of abstraction on the base syntax, you&rsquo;re essentially locking yourself into it&rsquo;s Domain-Specific Language (DSL).</a></li>
</ol>


<p>Blaming the use of a preprocessor on the coder&rsquo;s own bad habits, is like blaming traffic cameras for speeding. To get the best out of a tool, you must use it correctly. I&rsquo;m no shining example of this! I frequently try to nail pictures to the wall with a screwdriver; I&rsquo;m forever using an unnecessary amount of nesting in my <a href="http://thesassway.com/intermediate/avoid-nested-selectors-for-more-modular-css">Sass</a>.</p>

<p>You can&rsquo;t deny &lsquo;lock-in&rsquo; effort of adding a preprocessor to a project. In much the same way, you could argue that choosing to write an application in a language like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruby_(programming_language">Ruby</a>), locks the future development to the that language over say the base languages that Ruby is built on, like C or Java.</p>

<p>Well, that&rsquo;s not quite right, you could write a native extension for Ruby in C, if you wanted. Actually, this is why I use the SCSS syntax of Sass over SASS, and why I favour <a href="https://6to5.org/">6to5</a> over <a href="http://coffeescript.org/">CoffeeScript</a>. In both examples you can make use of all the wonderful syntactic sugar that the preprocessors provide, or ignore all of it and write in the base syntax. Let us not forget that we&rsquo;re never ever actually locked in by a good preprocessor, as its sole purpose is to generate the base syntax, so you can opt out at any time. &ldquo;Hey man, I don&rsquo;t need your syntactic goodness anymore, I&rsquo;m going to carry on with the base file&rdquo;.</p>

<p>A couple of issues are raised by my last paragraph:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>I love Ruby for the same reason that I don&rsquo;t like CoffeeScript.</strong> This is a weirdness that actually Lyza (the original post&rsquo;s author) will be helping me with later in this post. I have no interest in writing a line of C. I adore JavaScript and have never warmed to CoffeeScript as an alternative.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Why would you ever just  use the base syntax, if you&rsquo;d gone to the trouble of adding a preprocessor in the first place?</strong> I&rsquo;m completely non-dismissive of Lyza&rsquo;s arguments about the &lsquo;lock-in&rsquo; effect, or as I&rsquo;ve always thought of &lsquo;barrier to entry&rsquo; or &lsquo;learning curve&rsquo;. I work in a very talented dev team. We each come from different technological backgrounds and have our own preferences for tooling &amp; technology. If I&rsquo;m going to add a dependancy to the project, it better not be at the expense of a co-worker&rsquo;s ability to jump in.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Its at the point where Lyza starts talking about post-processors, that my angst starts to wain. I&rsquo;d never heard of <a href="https://github.com/postcss/postcss">PostCSS</a> or <a href="http://www.myth.io/">Myth</a> and I&rsquo;m pretty excited about both. I use <a href="http://compass-style.org/">Compass</a> a lot; the moment that hooked me was realising that I didn&rsquo;t  have to hack around with nonsense bits of CSS, to add cross browser support for <code>inline-block</code>. Maybe though its time for a slightly different approach, in much the same way that I write ES6 compliant JavaScript and have a &ldquo;preprocessor&rdquo; called 6to5 convert it into something most browsers can work with (I realise I&rsquo;m talking about ES5). Perhaps I should be writing compliant CSS3 and have one of these &ldquo;post-processors&rdquo; add all the &ldquo;make it work in older browser&rdquo; stuff.</p>

<p><em>Note: I&rsquo;ve used some of those double quotes divisively, I wonder if you noticed. It seems to me that the use of &ldquo;pre&rdquo; and &ldquo;post&rdquo; refers to the point at which the code is compliant to a standard. So, 6to5 is actually a post-processor. I went to the site for clarification. 6to5 actually refers to itself as a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Source-to-source_compiler">transpiler</a>, which is a marvellous way of avoiding a distinction that I care very little about.</em></p>

<p>In summation, Lyza&rsquo;s point (I believe) is that transpilers aren&rsquo;t there to cover up poor code, that diversity in one&rsquo;s approach (especially within a team) is good. If I&rsquo;m right, then I agree with her wholeheartedly in both regards. I don&rsquo;t agree with the negative connotations of so-called preprocessors &amp; post-proprocessors to get to these points though.</p>

<p>For my own part, Lyza&rsquo;s post is identified the different tacks I have been taking in my usage of transpilers in JavaScript and CSS. Its time to harmonise, where possible, starting with standards code and have the transpiler make it dirty. I won&rsquo;t be giving up my nesting anytime soon though.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Funniest Men of All Time - Rebuttal]]></title>
    <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/01/13/the-funniest-men-of-all-time-rebuttal/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-13T17:20:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/01/13/the-funniest-men-of-all-time-rebuttal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I saw the post <a href="http://thechive.com/2015/01/03/the-funniest-men-of-all-time-15-photos/">The funniest men of all time</a> pop up on my feed the other day, I was interested to see the awesome caliber of comic genius that would appear on such a strongly titled list.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><em>I think we can all safely assume going into this post, that the use of the word &lsquo;men&rsquo; is used strictly in the non-specific gender meaning of the word. Definitely.</em></p>

<p>Well that was weird. Let me take you through thought process, step by step:</p>

<ol>
<li>I don&rsquo;t know who half these people are.</li>
<li>After some research, they all appear to be North American.</li>
<li>I suspect, this is not a definitive list and heavily biased towards an american audience.</li>
<li>Richard Pryor would definitely make my list.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m gonna make a list.</li>
<li>Aren&rsquo;t there any funny North American women?</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m sure there is, I just can&rsquo;t think of their names at the moment.</li>
</ol>


<p>With my brain stuck on point 5, my own list must be heard! So my, nay THE list of funnest <del>men</del> humans of ALL TIME, with every chance that it may or may not be factually accurate, is:</p>

<h2>Richard Pryor</h2>

<p>The Chive got this one right, holy cow this man was funny. I first encountered Prior, as every good nerd only could have, in Superman 3.</p>

<h2>John Cleese</h2>

<p>Of all the Brits not to make any american list of funny people, it&rsquo;s John Cleese I&rsquo;m amazed was missing. He&rsquo;s done so much it&rsquo;s hard to name favourite, but I&rsquo;m going to try; Fawlty Towers. Or maybe Life of Brian.</p>

<p>Mr. Cleese also has a lot of interesting to say about creativity. He has certainly helped me look how I work creatively.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/yAwDWe7OIF8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p><img src="" alt="" /></p>

<h2>Sarah Silverman</h2>

<p>The Sarah Silverman Show has made me cry why laughter on more than one occasion. She does a surreal, irreverent style of comedy that&hellip; I wish there was more of it. (North American funny lady)</p>

<h2>Dylan Moran</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been in love with this man&rsquo;s comedy since Black Books. I like to believe it&rsquo;s actually how Dylan Moran lives his life.</p>

<h2>Dawn French</h2>

<p>Dawn French is an absolute must for this list, for so many reasons; from Comic Strip to Vicar of Dibley.</p>

<h2>Sean Lock</h2>

<p>I find Sean Lock&rsquo;s view of the world hysterical.</p>

<h2>Robin Williams</h2>

<p>He had me a Mork. I&rsquo;ve not stopped laughing since.</p>

<h2>Reginald D. Hunter</h2>

<p>I love what I perceive to be British humour, and struggle with a lot of &lsquo;established&rsquo; American comedians. Reginald D. Hunter just seems to get it.</p>

<h2>Morecambe &amp; Wise</h2>

<p>Is it fair to have a double act? If this was a countdown, there&rsquo;d be my number one.</p>

<h2>Eddie Izzard</h2>

<p>He was the comedy soundtrack to my twenties. It&rsquo;s the bird flying by the plane that gets me every time.</p>

<h2>Tommy Cooper</h2>

<p>&ldquo;What&rsquo;s this?&rdquo;
&ldquo;A dead one of these.&rdquo;</p>

<p>There is a lot of pressure writing a list like this. I&rsquo;ve given up trying to find CC images for them. I don&rsquo;t know how other people do it. Billy Crystal and Bill Bailey certainly belong on the list as well, I&rsquo;m not sure why I haven&rsquo;t added them.</p>

<p>Stephen Fry, who I find immensely funny, also isn&rsquo;t on the list. A travesty.</p>

<p>I love Richard Ayoade&rsquo;s dry sense of humour. Which reminds me, Katherine Parkinson makes The IT Crowd for me.</p>

<p>I think there is actually loads of people of missed out and I&rsquo;m also uncomfortable with the lack of order. It&rsquo;s not well presented list and you probably shouldn&rsquo;t take it too seriously.</p>

<p>I also find Adam Buxton extremely funny. I hope there is a new series of Bug in the works.</p>

<p>What would your list of funny people look like? I&rsquo;d love to hear.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
