<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rebuttal | Adventures in brine]]></title>
  <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/categories/rebuttal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-31T10:27:56+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://rich.k3r.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Richard Kimber]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Funniest Men of All Time - Rebuttal]]></title>
    <link href="http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/01/13/the-funniest-men-of-all-time-rebuttal/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-13T17:20:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://rich.k3r.me/blog/2015/01/13/the-funniest-men-of-all-time-rebuttal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I saw the post <a href="http://thechive.com/2015/01/03/the-funniest-men-of-all-time-15-photos/">The funniest men of all time</a> pop up on my feed the other day, I was interested to see the awesome caliber of comic genius that would appear on such a strongly titled list.</p>

<p><em>I think we can all safely assume going into this post, that the use of the word &lsquo;men&rsquo; is used strictly in the non-specific gender meaning of the word. Definitely.</em></p>

<p>Well that was weird. Let me take you through thought process, step by step:</p>

<ol>
<li>I don&rsquo;t know who half these people are.</li>
<li>After some research, they all appear to be North American.</li>
<li>I suspect, this is not a definitive list and heavily biased towards an american audience.</li>
<li>Richard Pryor would definitely make my list.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m gonna make a list.</li>
<li>Aren&rsquo;t there any funny North American women?</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m sure there is, I just can&rsquo;t think of their names at the moment.</li>
</ol>


<p>With my brain stuck on point 5, my own list must be heard! So my, nay THE list of funnest <del>men</del> humans of ALL TIME, with every chance that it may or may not be factually accurate, is:</p>

<h2>Richard Pryor</h2>

<p>The Chive got this one right, holy cow this man was funny. I first encountered Prior, as every good nerd only could have, in Superman 3.</p>

<h2>John Cleese</h2>

<p>Of all the Brits not to make any american list of funny people, it&rsquo;s John Cleese I&rsquo;m amazed was missing. He&rsquo;s done so much it&rsquo;s hard to name favourite, but I&rsquo;m going to try; Fawlty Towers. Or maybe Life of Brian.</p>

<p>Mr. Cleese also has a lot of interesting to say about creativity. He has certainly helped me look how I work creatively.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/yAwDWe7OIF8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p><img src="" alt="" /></p>

<h2>Sarah Silverman</h2>

<p>The Sarah Silverman Show has made me cry why laughter on more than one occasion. She does a surreal, irreverent style of comedy that&hellip; I wish there was more of it. (North American funny lady)</p>

<h2>Dylan Moran</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been in love with this man&rsquo;s comedy since Black Books. I like to believe it&rsquo;s actually how Dylan Moran lives his life.</p>

<h2>Dawn French</h2>

<p>Dawn French is an absolute must for this list, for so many reasons; from Comic Strip to Vicar of Dibley.</p>

<h2>Sean Lock</h2>

<p>I find Sean Lock&rsquo;s view of the world hysterical.</p>

<h2>Robin Williams</h2>

<p>He had me a Mork. I&rsquo;ve not stopped laughing since.</p>

<h2>Reginald D. Hunter</h2>

<p>I love what I perceive to be British humour, and struggle with a lot of &lsquo;established&rsquo; American comedians. Reginald D. Hunter just seems to get it.</p>

<h2>Morecambe &amp; Wise</h2>

<p>Is it fair to have a double act? If this was a countdown, there&rsquo;d be my number one.</p>

<h2>Eddie Izzard</h2>

<p>He was the comedy soundtrack to my twenties. It&rsquo;s the bird flying by the plane that gets me every time.</p>

<h2>Tommy Cooper</h2>

<p>&ldquo;What&rsquo;s this?&rdquo;
&ldquo;A dead one of these.&rdquo;</p>

<p>There is a lot of pressure writing a list like this. I&rsquo;ve given up trying to find CC images for them. I don&rsquo;t know how other people do it. Billy Crystal and Bill Bailey certainly belong on the list as well, I&rsquo;m not sure why I haven&rsquo;t added them.</p>

<p>Stephen Fry, who I find immensely funny, also isn&rsquo;t on the list. A travesty.</p>

<p>I love Richard Ayoade&rsquo;s dry sense of humour. Which reminds me, Katherine Parkinson makes The IT Crowd for me.</p>

<p>I think there is actually loads of people of missed out and I&rsquo;m also uncomfortable with the lack of order. It&rsquo;s not well presented list and you probably shouldn&rsquo;t take it too seriously.</p>

<p>I also find Adam Buxton extremely funny. I hope there is a new series of Bug in the works.</p>

<p>What would your list of funny people look like? I&rsquo;d love to hear.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
